William Short Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William Short Papers 1778-1853
MSS39891
Short, William, 1759-1849
20,000 items
64 containers plus 5 oversize
26 linear feet
32 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Secretary to President Thomas Jefferson, diplomat, and landowner. Diplomatic, financial, and personal correspondence, financial and business papers, memorabilia, and other papers relating to Short's activities as secretary to Jefferson, his diplomatic missions, and business interests.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, John, 1735-1826--Correspondence.; Carmichael, William, -1795--Correspondence.; Fulton, Robert, 1765-1815--Correspondence.; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849--Correspondence.; Godoy, Manuel de, príncipe de la Paz, 1767-1851--Correspondence.; Grayson, William, 1736-1790--Correspondence.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804--Correspondence.; Hull, Isaac, 1773-1843--Correspondence.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826--Correspondence.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834--Correspondence.; Madison, James, 1751-1836--Correspondence.; Monroe, James, 1758-1831--Correspondence.; Morris, Gouverneur, 1752-1816--Correspondence.; Nelson, William, 1760-1813--Correspondence.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809--Correspondence.; Pinckney, Thomas, 1750-1828--Correspondence.; Randolph, Edmund, 1753-1813--Correspondence.; Robinson, M. M. (Merritt M.), -1850--Correspondence.; Rutledge, John, 1739-1800--Correspondence.; Short family.; Short, Charles Wilkins, 1794-1863--Correspondence.; Short, William, 1759-1849.; Skipwith, Fulwar, 1765-1839--Correspondence.; Tocqueville, Alexis de, 1805-1859--Correspondence.; Washington, Bushrod, 1762-1829--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Colonization Society.
Subjects
Canals.; Debts, Public.; Finance, Public.; Finance.; Investments.; Land speculation--Kentucky.; Land speculation--New York (State); Land speculation--Ohio.; Land speculation--Virginia.; Railroads.
Places
France--Foreign relations--United States.; France--History--Revolution, 1789-1799.; Netherlands--Foreign relations--United States.; Russia--Foreign relations--United States.; Spain--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--France.; United States--Foreign relations--Netherlands.; United States--Foreign relations--Russia.; United States--Foreign relations--Spain.; Virginia--Politics and government.
Occupations
Diplomats.; Secretaries, Presidential.
Provenance
The papers of William Short, secretary to Thomas Jefferson, diplomat, and landowner, were purchased by the Library of Congress in 1898, 1910, and 1944.
Related Material
A related collection of Short papers was acquired at the time of the 1944 purchase and is part of the Short-Harrison-Symmes Families collection in the Manuscript Division of the Library.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William Short are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on thirty-two reels. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1759, Sept. 30 Born, Surry County, Va.
1776 Founder with others of Phi Beta Kappa (president, 1778-1781)
1779 Graduated, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Va.
1783 1784 Member, Executive Council of Virginia
1785 1789 Private secretary to Thomas Jefferson and later secretary of American legation, Paris, France
1789 1792 Chargé d’affaires, Paris, France
1790 Commissioned by Alexander Hamilton to handle debt funding
1792 1793 Minister at Hague, Netherlands
1793 1795 Joint commissioner with William Carmichael and later minister resident, Madrid, Spain
1795 1802 Resided in Paris, France
1802 Returned to the United States
1809 Appointment as minister to Russia rejected by the U.S. Senate
1809 1810 Resided in Paris, France
1810 Established residence in Philadelphia, Pa.
1810 1849 Amassed a fortune through investments and extensive land purchases
1849, Dec. 5 Died, Philadelphia, Pa.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Short (1759-1849) span the years 1778-1853. They include a large amount of material dated between 1785 and 1795, the years of Short’s diplomatic service in western Europe, as well as extensive documentation of his business activities after 1810. His papers consist chiefly of letters received, but there are also some copies of letters sent, 1785-1798, as well as various financial papers, including statements, receipts, checkbooks, and ledgers. Much of his correspondence while he was in Europe is with American diplomatic and political figures. There are also letters during this period from various European officials, chiefly in French or Spanish. The collection is organized in Bound Correspondence and Other Papers, Correspondence, Business Papers, Miscellany, and Oversize series.
In 1790 Alexander Hamilton entrusted Short with the negotiation and management of European loans to fund the public debt of the United States, and the two men conducted an extensive correspondence on the subject. Other topics in Short’s correspondence during his European years are conditions in Virginia under the Articles of Confederation, the events of the French Revolution, and incidents pertaining to American diplomatic relations with France and Spain. Short’s correspondence reveals the obstacles to the conduct of foreign relations resulting from the vagaries of trans-Atlantic communication in that era. While residing in Paris following his diplomatic service, and again following his abortive mission to Russia (the Senate refused to confirm the nomination of any minister to Saint Petersburg), Short established a wide circle of foreign friends, with whom he conducted a correspondence for many years thereafter, chiefly in French.
After his return to the United States in 1810, Short successfully pursued a career in investments that resulted eventually in a personal fortune of over one million dollars. He speculated in land in Ohio, Kentucky, and western New York and Virginia; he bought stock in canals, railroads, and banks; he held mortgages and loaned large sums at interest. His Dutch bankers speculated in American bonds on his account. These varied business activities required an extensive correspondence with his land agents (including his nephew, John Cleves Short), bankers, stockbrokers, and debtors. In addition to these letters, his business papers also include bills, accounts, financial statements, checkbooks, and ledgers. Short’s business papers provide considerable insight into the business practices and problems of an investor in the first half of the nineteenth century. They also include some information on Short’s moral and financial support of the program of the American Colonization Society.
A significant number of Short’s papers consist of his correspondence with Thomas Jefferson, who was, variously, his employer, adviser, and friend. Other correspondents of note include John Adams, James Madison, James Monroe (a classmate at William and Mary), Alexander Hamilton, Albert Gallatin, Don Diego de Gardoqui, Manuel de Godoy, the marquis de Lafayette, Alexis de Tocqueville, Michel-Guillaume St. Jean de Crévecoeur, Thomas Paine, William Carmichael, William Grayson, Fulwar Skipwith (his nephew), Gouverneur Morris, John Rutledge, Bushrod Washington, Nicholas Trist, Robert Fulton, Edmund Randolph, Thomas Pinckney, Issac Hull, and two Virginia friends, William Nelson and Merit Robinson. There are also a few letters from his nephew, Charles W. Short, a prominent botanist, and other members of his family.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
Bound Correspondence and Other Papers, 1778-1849
Correspondence, 1783-1849
Business Papers, 1782-1853
Miscellany, 1779-1836
Oversize, 1790-1831
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 17,058
- Bound Correspondence and Other Papers, 1778-1849 (Box 1-52, Reel 1-22)
  Official and general correspondence in bound volumes, including some copies of letters sent, and business papers and related material.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1778, July 8-1787, Jan. 7 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1787, Jan. 8-June 24 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - 1787, June 25-1788, Feb. 12 (Box 3, Reel 1)
  - 1788, Feb. 13-1789, June 30 (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - 1789, July 1-Dec. 28 (Box 5, Reel 2)
  - 1789, Dec. 29-1790, Apr. 11 (Box 6, Reel 3)
  - 1790 (Box 7, Reel 3)
    - Apr. 12-June 25 (Box 7, Reel 3)
    - June 26-Aug. 20 (Box 8, Reel 3-4)
    - Aug. 21-Oct. 20 (Box 9, Reel 4)
    - Oct. 21-Dec. 5 (Box 10, Reel 4)
  - 1790, Dec. 6-1791, Jan. 15 (Box 11, Reel 5)
  - 1791 (Box 12, Reel 5)
    - Jan. 16-Feb. 17 (Box 12, Reel 5)
    - Feb. 18-Apr. 13 (Box 13, Reel 5)
    - Apr. 14-June 7 (Box 14, Reel 6)
    - June 8-July 22 (Box 15, Reel 6)
    - July 23-Sept. 13 (Box 16, Reel 6)
    - Sept. 14-Nov. 24 (Box 17, Reel 7)
  - 1791 Nov. 25-1792, Jan. 25 See also Oversize (Box 18, Reel 7)
  - 1792 (Box 19, Reel 7)
    - Jan. 26-May 1 (Box 19, Reel 7)
    - May 12-Aug. 16 (Box 20, Reel 8)
    - Aug. 17-Oct. 22 (Box 21, Reel 8)
  - 1792, Oct. 23-1793, Feb. 16 (Box 22, Reel 8)
  - 1793, Feb. 17-July 12 (Box 23, Reel 9)
  - 1793, July 13-1794, Jan. 9 (Box 24, Reel 9)
  - 1794, Jan. 10-July 8 (Box 25, Reel 10)
  - 1794, July 9-Nov. 5 (Box 26, Reel 10)
  - 1794, Nov. 6-1795, Jan. 12 (Box 27, Reel 10)
  - 1795, Jan. 13-Apr. 28 (Box 28, Reel 11)
  - 1795, Apr. 29-Sept. 3 (Box 29, Reel 11)
  - 1795, Sept. 4-1798, Aug. 24 (Box 30, Reel 11-12)
  - 1798. Aug. 25-1802, Dec. 27 (Box 31, Reel 12)
  - 1802, Dec. 28-1805, July 13 See also Oversize (Box 32, Reel 12-13)
  - 1805, July 14-1807, July 15 (Box 33, Reel 13)
  - 1807, July 16-1810, Mar. 7 (Box 34, Reel 13-14)
  - 1810, Mar. 8-1811, June 18 (Box 35, Reel 13-14)
  - 1811, June 19-1813, Mar. 24 See also Oversize (Box 36, Reel 14-15)
  - 1813, Mar. 25-1815, Dec. 15 (Box 37, Reel 15)
  - 1815, Dec. 16-1818, Jan. 22 (Box 38, Reel 15)
  - 1818, Jan. 23-1819, Dec. 7 (Box 39, Reel 16)
  - 1819, Dec. 8-1821, June 16 (Box 40, Reel 16)
  - 1821, June 17-1823, Apr. 22 (Box 41, Reel 17)
  - 1823, Apr. 23-1824, Nov. 26 (Box 42, Reel 17)
  - 1824, Nov. 27-1826, June 20 (Box 43, Reel 18)
  - 1826, June 21-1828, Apr. 2 (Box 44, Reel 18)
  - 1828, Apr. 3-1829, Nov. 13 (Box 45, Reel 19)
  - 1829, Nov. 14-1831, Nov. 2 (Box 46, Reel 19)
  - 1831, Nov. 3-1833, Nov. 4 (Box 47, Reel 20)
  - 1833, Nov. 5-1835, May 17 (Box 48, Reel 20)
  - 1835, May 18-1837, Aug. 10 (Box 49, Reel 21)
  - 1837, Aug. 11-1839, Dec. 5 (Box 50, Reel 21)
  - 1839, Dec. 6-1842, Dec. 30 (Box 51, Reel 22)
  - 1842, Dec. 31-1849, Nov. 7, undated See also Oversize (Box 52, Reel 22)
- Correspondence, 1783-1849 (Box 53-56, Reel 23-26)
  Official, general, business, and family correspondence.
  - 1783-1814, (6 folders) (Box 53, Reel 23)
  - 1815-1824, (7 folders) (Box 54, Reel 24)
  - 1827-1837, (5 folders) (Box 55, Reel 25)
  - 1838-1849, (6 folders) (Box 56, Reel 26)
- Business Papers, 1782-1853 (Box 57-64, Reel 27-32)
  Bills, accounts, receipts, and other financial papers. Arranged chronologically, followed by bankbooks, checkbooks, and ledgers
  Arranged chronologically, followed by bankbooks, checkbooks, and ledgers
  - Accounts, bills, and receipts (Box 57, Reel 27)
    - 1782-1818, (10 folders) (Box 57, Reel 27)
    - 1819-1827, (9 folders) (Box 58, Reel 28)
    - 1828-1834, (7 folders) (Box 59, Reel 28-29)
    - 1835-1842, (8 folders) (Box 60, Reel 29)
    - 1843-1853, undated (including estate), (4 folders) (Box 61, Reel 30)
    - Miscellaneous personal accounts; negative photocopies; and other financial papers, chiefly fragments, 1792-1803, undated (Box 61, Reel 30)
  - Bankbooks (Box 61, Reel 30)
  - Checkbooks, (2 folders) (Box 61, Reel 30)
  - Checkbooks, (5 folders) (Box 62, Reel 31)
  - Checkbooks, (2 folders) (Box 63, Reel 31-32)
  - Ledgers, (2 folders) (Box 63, Reel 31-32)
  - Ledger, 1834-1849 (Box 64, Reel 32)
- Miscellany, 1779-1836 (Box 64, Reel 32)
  Short’s catalog of Thomas Jefferson’s library, list of Short’s library, and extracts of letters and other miscellany.
  Arranged by type of material, followed by an oversize box containing Short’s college diploma, his diplomatic commissions, and a letter.
  - Short’s catalog of Jefferson’s library with a bound negative photocopy (Box 64, Reel 32)
  - List of Short’s library (Box 64, Reel 32)
  - Extracts of letters, incomplete manuscripts, and negative photocopies, 1785-1836, undated (Box 64, Reel 32)
  - Diploma, William and Mary College, Williamsburg, Va., 1779, Apr. 15 See Oversize (Box 64, Reel 32)
  - Diplomatic commissions, 1790-1808 See Oversize (Box 64, Reel 32)
  - Letter of Edward Everett concerning the founding of Phi Beta Kappa, 1831 See Oversize (Box 64, Reel 32)
- Oversize, 1790-1831 (Box OV 1-OV 5)
  A report, maps, diplomas, diplomatic commission, and letter from Edward Everett.
  Arranged and described according to the series, container, or folder from which the items were removed.
  Oversize items were filmed in the location from which they were removed.
  - Correspondence and Other Papers (Box OV 1)
    - Report of the secretary of the Treasury, 1792, Jan. 23 (Container 18) (Box OV 1)
    - Map of land belonging to I. B. Church, New York, 1803 (Container 32) (Box OV 2)
    - Platt map of Ohio lands, 1813 (Container 36) (Box OV 3)
    - Map of Town No. 6 in Scriba Patent, undated (Container 52) (Box OV 4)
  - Business Papers (Container 64) (Box OV 5)
    - Diploma, William and Mary College, Williamsburg, Va., 1779, Apr. 15 1779, Apr. 15 (Box OV 5)
    - Diplomatic commissions, 1790-1808 (Box OV 5)
    - Letter of Edward Everett concerning the founding of Phi Beta Kappa, 1831 (Box OV 5)